<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-02-10T20:10:22-05:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">ndKline</title><subtitle>Nicholas is a Senior Application Developer at Solar Innovations where he brings a passion for modern web development, user interface design, and technology evangelism (NodeJS). He takes a mobile first approach to web application development, always trying to reach an optimal user experience across platforms and designs to maximize accessibility.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Highly Optimized SSG Website</title><link href="/blog/2018/01/31/highly-optimized-ssg-website.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Highly Optimized SSG Website" /><published>2018-01-31T13:17:07-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-31T13:17:07-05:00</updated><id>/blog/2018/01/31/highly-optimized-ssg-website</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2018/01/31/highly-optimized-ssg-website.html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last two weeks I have been rebuiling a &lt;a href=&quot;https://greenhouse.planning.solar/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;website meant for walking users through the greenhouse planning process&lt;/a&gt;. Most of the content was redeveloped from &lt;a href=&quot;http://greenhouseplanning.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the old site&lt;/a&gt;. Take a second and look at both and note the overt user experience improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site was designed to be highly optimized, using a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.staticgen.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Static Site Generator&lt;/a&gt; as it’s pseudo content management system. This is adventageous because non-technical users will never update the site, only a web developer. So we’re able to take the compilation out from the runtime of the server and precompile all the assets statically. This means pages get served to the client much quick, because they don’t have to wait for the server to generate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site performs exceedingly well in speed tests. Using Google’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/speed/pagespeed/insights/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PageSpeed Insights&lt;/a&gt;, I was able to bring the pagespeeds to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mobile Speed: 99/100&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Desktop Speed: 98/100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through another performance grading tool, &lt;a href=&quot;https://website.grader.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Website Grader&lt;/a&gt;, the site performed equally as well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Performance: 27/30&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mobile: 30/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SEO: 30/30&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Security: 10/10&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my network I’m able to load the homepage in ~0.5 seconds with a page size of 334KB. The pages are being served up through an &lt;a href=&quot;http://nginx.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NGINX&lt;/a&gt; webserver. The sites are hosted on a scaleable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This website structure is highly advantageous with how well optimized it can be. Future plans would be to include a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comparison_of_JavaScript_frameworks&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;JavaScript Framework&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representational_state_transfer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;RESTful services&lt;/a&gt; for more dynamic content that spans several websites. I’m leaning towards &lt;a href=&quot;https://angularjs.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;AngularJS&lt;/a&gt; however &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.emberjs.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;EmberJS&lt;/a&gt; might make more sense for this usecase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a few other hidden surprises within this latest website build. I’m hoping to show these off in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Over the last two weeks I have been rebuiling a website meant for walking users through the greenhouse planning process. Most of the content was redeveloped from the old site. Take a second and look at both and note the overt user experience improvements.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">RESTful APIs</title><link href="/blog/2017/03/20/restful-apis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RESTful APIs" /><published>2017-03-20T14:17:07-04:00</published><updated>2017-03-20T14:17:07-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2017/03/20/restful-apis</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2017/03/20/restful-apis.html">&lt;p&gt;If you’re a front-end developer, chances are you’ve worked with an API, whether it’s RESTful or not is another story that will not be addressed here. What I will discuss is how elegantly RESTful architecture makes backend to front-end relationship an ideal structure for development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a front-end developer at Columbia University, I’ve had the pleasure of working with other developers’ APIs. Now, the API might not be considered RESTful that we were working with (a level 1 or 2 on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://martinfowler.com/articles/richardsonMaturityModel.html&quot;&gt;Richardson Maturity Model&lt;/a&gt;) but the structure is close enough. The project allowed for me to focus solely on the user experience and design of the client side experience without having to worry about server side template rendering, using &lt;a href=&quot;https://angularjs.org/&quot;&gt;AngularJS&lt;/a&gt; as the front-end framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The API I was connecting to was populated with dummy data while he worked on writing the backend logic. As he finished the results changed organically as it was committed and pushed. But how is this better than the typical server-side template processing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, for one the API creates a clear distinction between front-end and backend. When the templates are processed on the server side, developers can step on each other’s toes. In Drupal, for example, the addition of a module can change how some results are written completely, making the front-end dev adjust their code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another bonus for RESTful APIs is versioning. If major changes occur to the structure of the API, you can progress to another version number without retiring the old API until you’re ready. While this can be done with most LAMP frameworks, it’s a more convoluted process and again, messy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Processing the templates on the client side saves you server processing resources. For large scale applications, this can mean hundreds of dollars. It also gives you more flexibility with scaling, letting your resources focus on the computations and leaving the client to render the aesthetics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">If you’re a front-end developer, chances are you’ve worked with an API, whether it’s RESTful or not is another story that will not be addressed here. What I will discuss is how elegantly RESTful architecture makes backend to front-end relationship an ideal structure for development.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Football to Soccer Uniforms</title><link href="/blog/2017/02/20/football-to-soccer-uniforms.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Football to Soccer Uniforms" /><published>2017-02-20T11:29:11-05:00</published><updated>2017-02-20T11:29:11-05:00</updated><id>/blog/2017/02/20/football-to-soccer-uniforms</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2017/02/20/football-to-soccer-uniforms.html">&lt;p&gt;Recently my younger brother was featured by FoxSports: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foxsports.com/soccer/gallery/what-would-every-nfl-team-look-like-with-a-soccer-kit-020517&quot;&gt;What would every NFL team look like with a soccer kit?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Recently my younger brother was featured by FoxSports: What would every NFL team look like with a soccer kit?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PA to NYC</title><link href="/blog/2017/02/02/pa-to-nyc.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PA to NYC" /><published>2017-02-02T11:48:07-05:00</published><updated>2017-02-02T11:48:07-05:00</updated><id>/blog/2017/02/02/pa-to-nyc</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2017/02/02/pa-to-nyc.html">&lt;p&gt;There have been several major updates since I last posted. I moved from the center of Pennsylvania to the heart of the American empire, NYC. Since moving here I’ve seen countless concerts, gone to talks at Google’s NYC HQ, and sampled foods from all over the world. And given everything that’s been happening to the country, I’ve branched away from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.progcode.co/&quot;&gt;Progressive Coders Network&lt;/a&gt; and founded a new political development group. More to come on that in the coming weeks though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A little about the new job…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before at Penn State I wore all the hats. And by that I mean I had sysadmin, programmer, designer, QA, webmaster, information architect, etc… responsibilities. Never could I find time to focus on any one field, I found myself overloaded quickly, and at a less than desirable pay rate. Columbia University found me and relived a lot of that stress. I’m now on their Interactive Services team as a front-end engineer. We’re mostly working in Drupal, with some headless builds and some AngularJS/RESTful apps filling in gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all the transition was smooth, busy, but smooth. I’ll be visiting Penn State this weekend for a bit of fun and to pickup a few things. Everything went well and that’s all I can ask for.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="PA," /><category term="NYC," /><category term="job" /><category term="upgrade," /><category term="political" /><category term="action" /><summary type="html">There have been several major updates since I last posted. I moved from the center of Pennsylvania to the heart of the American empire, NYC. Since moving here I’ve seen countless concerts, gone to talks at Google’s NYC HQ, and sampled foods from all over the world. And given everything that’s been happening to the country, I’ve branched away from the Progressive Coders Network and founded a new political development group. More to come on that in the coming weeks though.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Internship Aggregate, UX, and AngularJS – A Story on Blowing Minds</title><link href="/blog/2016/10/13/internship-aggregate-ux-and-angularjs-a-story-on-blowing-minds.markdown.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Internship Aggregate, UX, and AngularJS -- A Story on Blowing Minds" /><published>2016-10-13T10:32:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-13T10:32:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2016/10/13/internship-aggregate-ux-and-angularjs-a-story-on-blowing-minds.markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2016/10/13/internship-aggregate-ux-and-angularjs-a-story-on-blowing-minds.markdown.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;reception-of-a-new-tool&quot;&gt;Reception of a New Tool&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve been getting awesome feedback on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ndkline/rhs_intern_db&quot;&gt;Internship Aggregate&lt;/a&gt; I launched at the end of summer. The students are telling faculty/staff in that unit how much they like the tool, how easy it is to use, etc. Basically they’re confirming the UX has been improved significantly since the original ColdFusion service launched. Best part is, I could scale the new architecture to serve the whole University basically overnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the kicker: The unit that requested it wanted it behind a login so no one outside their unit could use it or even see it. PSU bureaucracy at its finest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, I’m very pleased with the application’s reception amongst its users. Feel free to fork the project on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ndkline/rhs_intern_db&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technical-overview&quot;&gt;Technical Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was brought into this project by our lead programmer when the request was made for the update to an internship database. They were wanting an update to the look and feel of the site, essentially a UX overhaul. The old application was built in ColdFusion at around the turn of the century, so needless to say it in fact did need a huge facelift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We decided to retain the backend “CMS” portion of the application and expose the content via a RESTful API. Once we got that working, I took the front-end and Joe (the other programmer) took updating the backend. We were able to work incredibly well since the my front-end design is only dependent upon the API. It was one of the most fluid front-end/backend collaborations I’ve experienced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RESTful API and CMS were built in, or remained in, ColdFusion while I used AngularJS as a front-end framework and Zurb Foundation for scaffolding.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="ColdFusion," /><category term="AngularJS," /><category term="Restful," /><category term="API," /><category term="Internship" /><category term="Aggregate," /><category term="Zurb," /><category term="Foundation" /><summary type="html">Reception of a New Tool</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Launching the Center for Education and Civil Rights Website</title><link href="/blog/2016/10/05/new-post.markdown.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Launching the Center for Education and Civil Rights Website" /><published>2016-10-05T14:51:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-05T14:51:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2016/10/05/new-post.markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2016/10/05/new-post.markdown.html">&lt;p&gt;Today we are launching the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cecr.ed.psu.edu/&quot;&gt;Center for Education and Civil Rights&lt;/a&gt; (CECR) website. &lt;a href=&quot;http://rossdc.com/&quot;&gt;Ross Designs and Consulting&lt;/a&gt; was contracted to build the site and produced quality work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site resides under one of the servers I administer and maintain. We’re excited to be expanding our Drupal infrastructure in a more maintainable direction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Today we are launching the Center for Education and Civil Rights (CECR) website. Ross Designs and Consulting was contracted to build the site and produced quality work.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bootstrap Mini-Site Buildout</title><link href="/blog/2016/10/04/bootstrap-mini-site-buildout.markdown.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bootstrap Mini-Site Buildout" /><published>2016-10-04T11:14:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-04T11:14:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2016/10/04/bootstrap-mini-site-buildout.markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2016/10/04/bootstrap-mini-site-buildout.markdown.html">&lt;p&gt;One of our techs at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cetc.ed.psu.edu&quot;&gt;Carrara Education Technology Center&lt;/a&gt; is tasked with giving a start of semester presentation to all new-coming grad students. Typically he has a PowerPoint presentation he’ll update yearly and print slides out for the students to reference. This year we tried something different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a little bandwidth available so I offered to spin up a &lt;a href=&quot;http://getbootstrap.com/&quot;&gt;Twitter Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; site. Millennials have a litany of devices to view a webpage on, the documents still can be printed if desired, and Bootstrap is easy so why not?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So over the course of a day or so I threw together the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ed.psu.edu/resources/&quot;&gt;Understanding College of Education Resources&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Bootstrap," /><category term="Single" /><category term="Page," /><category term="College" /><category term="of" /><category term="Education," /><category term="CETC" /><summary type="html">One of our techs at the Carrara Education Technology Center is tasked with giving a start of semester presentation to all new-coming grad students. Typically he has a PowerPoint presentation he’ll update yearly and print slides out for the students to reference. This year we tried something different.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">UX Research and Design MicroMasters Program</title><link href="/blog/2016/10/03/ux-research-and-design-micromasters-program.markdown.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UX Research and Design MicroMasters Program" /><published>2016-10-03T11:44:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-03T11:44:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2016/10/03/ux-research-and-design-micromasters-program.markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2016/10/03/ux-research-and-design-micromasters-program.markdown.html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edx.org/micromasters/michiganx-user-experience-ux-research-and-design&quot;&gt;User Experience Research and Design MicroMasters&lt;/a&gt; program via &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edx.org/&quot;&gt;edX&lt;/a&gt; and backed by &lt;a href=&quot;http://umich.edu/&quot;&gt;the University of Michigan&lt;/a&gt; begins tomorrow. I’ve enrolled for certification within the program and will be taking classes along side a coworker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MicroMasters is a series of 9 courses starting Oct. 4 and going until August.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a web developer I have worn many hats; front-end dev, graphic designer, programmer, full stack developer, backend dev, systems administrator, and dev ops engineer. I’ve excelled in each of those fields because I have always taken a empathetic, user first approach to software development. This program only serves as accreditation to skills I already have and regularly use.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="UX," /><category term="UX" /><category term="Research," /><category term="User" /><category term="Experience," /><category term="UX" /><category term="Design," /><category term="University" /><category term="of" /><category term="Michigan," /><category term="edX" /><summary type="html">The User Experience Research and Design MicroMasters program via edX and backed by the University of Michigan begins tomorrow. I’ve enrolled for certification within the program and will be taking classes along side a coworker.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TheAgora Meets Pantheon</title><link href="/blog/2016/10/02/here-s-a-new-post.markdown.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TheAgora Meets Pantheon" /><published>2016-10-02T12:40:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-02T12:40:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2016/10/02/here-s-a-new-post.markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2016/10/02/here-s-a-new-post.markdown.html">&lt;p&gt;Today TheAgora has officially moved to &lt;a href=&quot;https://pantheon.io/&quot;&gt;Pantheon&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Pantheon," /><category term="Drupal," /><category term="theagora" /><summary type="html">Today TheAgora has officially moved to Pantheon!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CETC Alpha Launch</title><link href="/blog/2016/09/27/here-s-a-new-post.markdown.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CETC Alpha Launch" /><published>2016-09-27T12:40:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-09-27T12:40:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2016/09/27/here-s-a-new-post.markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2016/09/27/here-s-a-new-post.markdown.html">&lt;p&gt;The Carrara Education Technology Center is proud to announce the Alpha launch of it’s website found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cetc.ed.psu.edu/&quot;&gt;cetc.ed.psu.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since my start with the Carrara Education Technology Center, or CETC, I have been tasked with designing and developing a new web presence for the College of Education. If you visit their &lt;a href=&quot;ed.psu.edu&quot;&gt;current site&lt;/a&gt; and explore a little bit, you will notice it’s rather challenging to navigate to information that would be desirable to most types of people that would visit the site, students, faculty, prospective students, etc… It’s easy to drill down into content and get lost. Content is also slow to be written, edited, and published. The technical side of our infrastructure is even worse; We run Plone on Windows servers with a caching Varnish (Linux) server. This is a gross simplification of our current stack, however the point I’m making is that the bar of entry on any of our projects is rather steep for most developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve these issues I decoupled our website’s public views and CMS to focus on the content creation process. I nixed Plone and our expensive Windows servers for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drupal.org/&quot;&gt;Drupal&lt;/a&gt; 7 and comparatively Linux servers. Within Drupal I was able to rapidly define content creation workflows for our staff and expose the data via &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representational_state_transfer&quot;&gt;RESTful services&lt;/a&gt;. By splitting the CMS and public views apart, I am able to focus development on either backend and front-end. The backend would be Drupal and front-end will be in &lt;a href=&quot;https://angularjs.org/&quot;&gt;AngularJS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://facebook.github.io/react/&quot;&gt;ReactJS&lt;/a&gt;, or another front-end JavaScript framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CETC website will serve as the Drupal portion of the previously described stack. Any other site we build will consume the content via the RESTful service. As we grow our content, I will be able to build a specialized team around this architecture. The backend team will work within Drupal and front-end team will focus on AngularJS/ReactJS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Drupal," /><category term="d7," /><category term="drupal" /><category term="7," /><category term="Plone," /><category term="RESTful," /><category term="CETC," /><category term="Carrara" /><category term="Education" /><category term="Technology" /><category term="Center," /><category term="CMS," /><category term="Headless" /><summary type="html">The Carrara Education Technology Center is proud to announce the Alpha launch of it’s website found at cetc.ed.psu.edu.</summary></entry></feed>